Now, in here we see that many references to black saints:
Aqui a gente vê referência aos santos pretos, né?
St. Benedict the Moor, St. Elesbaan of Axum,
São Benedito, Santo Elesbão,
Our Lady of Sorrows, St. Roch...
Nossa Senhora das Dores, São Roque...
You can notice how in this church, the Rosary of Black People,
Então, há que se observar também que
there are many Catholic saints, which are very related
na Igreja do Rosário a gente vê a presença de vários santos católicos
to syncretic religions of African descent.
que têm muita relação com o sincretismo das religiões de matrizes africanas.
For example, St. Roch is syncretized with Obaluaê deity,
Por exemplo, São Roque, sincretizado com Obaluaê
St. Barbara with Iansã deity.
Santa Barbara é sincretizada com Iansã.
St. anne, with Nanã.
Nossa senhora de Santana que é sincretizada com Nanã.
And it's a worship of black saints
E a devoção dos santos pretos, né?
which have become symbols of the resistance movements
Que acabaram se tornando símbolos de resistência
to the population of black slaves.
para a população preta escravizada.
Here we have St. Benedict, worshiped
São Benedito
not only by the black brotherhoods
que é um santo de referência não só para as irmandades
but also in the Congados, feast-day dramatized celebrations.
mas também para as coroações de Reis.
Here we also have St. George, a very well known saint both to
São Jorge, que é um santo muito presente no catolicismo popular
popular catholicism and to religions of African descent, such as Umbanda.
e também nas religiões de matrizes africanas como a Umbanda.